by CHAPTER 5 THE CRY IN THE CORRIDOR At first each day which passed
by for Mary Lennox was exactly like the others. Every morning she awoke in her
tapestried room and found Martha kneeling upon the hearth building her
fire; every morning she ate her breakfast in the nursery which had nothing amusing
in it; and after each breakfast she gazed out of the window across to the huge
Moore which seemed to spread out on all sides and climb up to the sky, and after
she had stared for a while she realized that if she did not go out she would
have to stay in and do nothing— —and so she went out. She did not know that this
was the best thing she could have done, and she did not know that, when she began
to walk quickly or even run along the paths and down the avenue, she was
stirring her slow blood and making making herself stronger by fighting with
the wind which swept down from the Moore She ran only to make herself warm, and
she hated the wind which rushed at her face and roared and held her back as if
it were some giant she could not see. But the big breaths of rough fresh air blown
over the heather filled her lungs with something which was good for her whole
thin body and whipped some red color into her cheeks and brightened her dull
eyes when she did not know anything about it. But after a few days spent
almost entirely out of doors she wakened one morning knowing what it was to be
hungry, and when she sat down to her breakfast she did not glance
disdainfully at her porridge and push it away, but took up her spoon and began to
eat it and went on eating it until her bowl was
empty thou got on well enough with that this morning didn't th said said
Martha. "It tastes nice today said Mary, feeling a little surprised
herself. "It's the air of the Moore that's giving the stomach for th victuals,"
answered Martha. "It's lucky for thee that th got vitual as well as
appetite. There's been 12 in our cottage has had the stomach and nothing to put
in it. You go on playing you out of doors every day and you'll get some flesh on
your bones and you won't be so yell I don't play," said Mary. "I have nothing to
play with nothing to play with!" exclaimed Martha. "Our children plays with sticks
and stones. They just runs about and shouts and looks at
things." Mary did not shout, but she looked at things. There was nothing else to do.
She walked round and round the gardens and wandered about the paths in the park.
Sometimes she looked for Ben weather staff but though several times she saw
him at work he was too busy to look at her or was too
sirly Once when she was walking toward him he picked up his spade and turned
away as if he did it on purpose. One place she went to oftener than to any
other. It was the long walk outside the gardens with the walls around
them. There were bare flower beds on either side of it and against the walls ivy grew
thickly. There was one part of the wall where the creeping dark green leaves
were more bushy than elsewhere. It seemed as if for a long time that part had been
neglected. The rest of it had been clipped and made to look neat, but at
this lower end of the walk it had not been trimmed at
all. A few days after she had talked to Ben weather staff Mary stopped to notice
this and wondered why it was so. She had just paused and was looking
up at a long spray of ivy swinging in the wind when she saw a gleam of scarlet
and heard a brilliant chirp, and there, on the top of the wall, perched Ben
Weatherstaff's robin red breast tilting forward to look at her with his small head on one
side. "Oh!" she cried out, "is it you— —is it
you?" And it did not seem at all queer to
her that she spoke to him as if she was sure that he would understand and answer
her. He did answer. He twittered and chirped and hopped along the wall as if
he were telling her all sorts of things.
It seemed to Mistress Mary as if she understood him, too, though he was not speaking in
words. It was as if he said: "Good morning!
Isn't the wind nice? Isn't the sun nice?
Isn't everything nice?
Let us both chirp and hop and twitter.
Come on! Come on!" Mary began to laugh, and as he hopped and took little flights
along the wall she ran after him. Poor little thin sow ugly Mary— —she actually
looked almost pretty for a moment. "I like you! I like you!" she cried out, pattering
down the walk; and she chirped and tried to whistle, which last she did not know
how to do in the least. But the robin seemed to be quite satisfied and chirped
and whistled back at her. At last he spread his wings and made a darting
flight to the top of a tree, where he perched and sang
loudly. That reminded Mary of the first time she had seen him. He had been
swinging on a treetop then and she had been standing in the orchard. Now she was
on the other side of the orchard and standing in the path outside a wall— —much lower down—
—and there was the same tree inside. "It's in the garden no one can go
into," she said to herself. "It's the garden without a door. He lives in there. How I
wish I could see what it is like!" She ran
up the walk to the green door she had entered the first morning. Then she ran
down the path through the other door and then into the orchard, and when she stood
and looked up there was the tree on the other other side of the wall, and there
was the robin just finishing his song and beginning to pin his feathers with
his beak. "It is the garden," she said I'm sure it is." She walked round and looked closely
at that side of the orchard wall, but she only found what she had found before—
—that there was no door in it. Then she ran through the kitchen Gardens again
and out into the walk outside the long Ivy covered wall, and she walked to the
end of it and looked at it, but there was
no door; and then she walked to the other end, looking again, but there was no door.
"It's very queer," she said. "Ben weather staff said there was no
door and there is no door. But there must have been one 10 years ago, because Mr.
Craven buried the key." This gave her so much to think of
that she began to be quite interested and feel that she was not sorry that she
had come to mleth Manor. In India she had always felt hot
and too languid to care much about anything. The fact was that the fresh
wind from the Moore had begun to blow the cobwebs out of her young brain and
to waken her up a little. She stayed out of doors nearly
all day, and when she sat down to her supper at night she felt hungry and drowsy and
comfortable. She did not feel cross when Martha chattered away. She felt as if she
rather liked to hear her, and at last she thought she would ask her a question. She
asked it after she had finished her supper and had sat down on the Hearth rug before the
fire. "Why did Mr. Craven hate the garden?"
she said. She had made Martha stay with her and Martha had not objected at all.
She was very young, and used to a crowded cottage full of brothers and sisters, and
she found it dull in the great servants' hall downstairs where the footman and
upper housemaids made fun of her Yorkshire speech and looked upon her as
a common little thing, and sat and whispered among themselves. Martha liked
to talk, and the strange child who had lived in India, and been waited upon by
"blacks," was novelty enough to attract her.
She sat down on the Heth herself without waiting to be asked. "Art th thinking about that garden
yet?" she said. "I knew thou would. That was just the way with me when I first heard
about it." "Why did he hate it?" Mary persisted. Martha tucked her feet under
her and made herself quite comfortable. "Listen to the wind weing
around the house," she said. "You could be
stand up on the mo if you was out on it tonight Mary did not know what wein
meant until she listened, and then she understood.
It must mean that hollow shuddering sort of roar which rushed round and around
the house as if the giant no one could see were buffeting it and beating at the
walls and windows to try to break in. But one knew he could not get in, and
somehow it made one feel very safe and warm inside a room with a red coold
fire. "But why did he hate it so?" she asked, after she had listened. She intended to
know if Martha did. Then Martha gave up her store of
knowledge. "Mind," she said, "Mrs. Medlock said it's not to be talked about. There's lots
of things in this place that's not to be talked over. That's Mr. Craven's orders.
His troubles are n servants' business, he says. But for the garden he wouldn't be
like he is. It was Mrs. Craven's garden that she had made when first they were
married and she just loved it and they used to 'tend the flowers themselves and
none of the gardeners was ever let to go
in. Him and her used to go in and shut the door and stay there hours and hours
reading and talking and she was just a bit of a girl and there was an old tree
with a branch bent like a seat on it and
she made roses grow over it and she used to sit there. But one day when she was
sitting there the branch broke and she fell on the ground and was hurt so bad
that next day she died the doctors thought he'd go out of his mind and die,
too. That's why he hates it. No one's never gone in since and he won't let
anyone talk about it." Mary did not ask any more questions.
She looked at the red fire and listened to the wind
weing It seemed to be weing louder than ever. At that moment a very good thing
was happening to her. Four good things had happened to her, in fact, since she
came to MTH Manor. She had felt as if she had understood a robin and that he had
understood her; she had run in the wind until her blood had grown warm; she had
been healthily hungry for the first time in her life; and she had found out what
it was to be sorry for someone She was getting on. But as she was listening to
the wind she began to listen to something else. She did not know what it was,
because at first first she could scarcely distinguish it from the wind
itself. It was a curious sound— —it seemed almost as if a child were crying
somewhere. Sometimes the wind sounded rather like a child
crying, but presently Mistress Mary felt quite sure that this sound was inside
the house, not outside it. It was far away, but it was
inside. She turned around and looked at Martha. "Do you hear anyone crying?" she
said. Martha suddenly looked confused. "No," she answered. "It's the
wind. Sometimes it sounds like as if someone was lost on the mo and wailing
It's got all sorts of sounds." "But listen," said Mary. "It's in the house— —down one of
those long corridors." And at that very moment a door must have been opened somewhere
downstairs for a great rushing draft blew along the passage and the door door
of the room they sat in was blown open with a crash, and as they both jumped to
their feet the light was blown out and the crying sound was swept down the far
corridor so that it was to be heard more plainly than
ever. "There!" said Mary. "I told you so! It is someone crying— —and it isn't a grownup
person." Martha ran and shut the door and turned the key, but before she did it
they both heard the sound of a door in some far passage shutting with a bang,
and then everything was quiet, for even the wind ceased weing for a few
moments. "It was the wind," said Martha stubbornly and if it wasn't, it was
little Betty Butterworth the skullery maid She's had the toothache all
day." But something troubled and awkward in her manner made Mistress Mary stare
very hard at at her. She did not believe she was speaking the